### Soumya Sanyal

CONTACT Information MALL Lab, CDS

Inidan Institute of Science, Bangalore

Email: sanyal.soumya8@gmail.com Website: github.com/soumyasanyal

RESEARCH INTERESTS I am broadly interested in Deep Learning on Graphs and Natural Language Processing. My recent research has focused on learning and inference over graphs, knowledge graph completion and representation learning of molecules and materials.

EDUCATION

Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur, India2012 – 2016B.Tech in Electronics and Electrical CommunicationCGPA: 8.98/10Minor in Computer ScienceCGPA: 8.92/10

REFEREED CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

- [1] <u>Soumya Sanyal</u>\*, Shikhar Vashishth\*, Vikram Nitin, Nilesh Agrawal, and Partha Talukdar. **InteractE:** Improving Convolution-based Knowledge Graph Embeddings by Increasing Feature Interactions. Thirty-Fourth AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI-20), New York, USA. [Paper]
- [2] Ekagra Ranjan, Soumya Sanyal, and Partha Talukdar. ASAP: Adaptive Structure Aware Pooling for Learning Hierarchical Graph Representations. Thirty-Fourth AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI-20), New York, USA. [Fix Paper link]

REFEREED WORKSHOP PAPERS [3] Soumya Sanyal, Janakiraman Balachandran, Naganand Yadati, Abhishek Kumar, Padmini Rajagopalan, Suchismita Sanyal, and Partha Talukdar. MT-CGCNN: Integrating Crystal Graph Convolutional Neural Network with Multitask Learning for Material Property Prediction.

NeurIPS 2018 Workshop on Machine Learning for Molecules and Materials, Montreal, Canada. [Paper | Code]

Preprints

- [4] Soumya Sanyal\*, Shikhar Vashishth\*, Vikram Nitin, and Partha Talukdar. Composition-based Multi-Relational Graph Convolutional Networks. (currently under submission at ICLR 2020)
  [Paper]
- [5] Zhiqing Sun\*, Shikhar Vashishth\*, <u>Soumya Sanyal</u>\*, Partha Talukdar, and Yiming Yang. A Reevaluation of Knowledge Graph Completion Methods . [Paper]

EMPLOYMENT

Indian Institute Science, Bangalore, India

Aug 2018 – Present

Research Assistant, MALL Labs

Hosted by *Prof. Partha Talukdar*, Department of Computational and Data Sciences, IISc (supported by Shell grant). Worked on graph neural networks and its applications in knowledge graph completion, protein refinement and material discovery.

Goldman Sachs Services Private Limited, Bangalore, India

Jun 2016 – Jul 2018

Senior Analyst, Equities Risk Management

Part of the global team responsible for developing and managing the risk infrastructure of the equities desk. Worked on financial risk modeling, risk engines and risk monitoring.

RESEARCH PROJECTS

# InteractE: Improving Convolution-based Knowledge Graph Embeddings by Increasing Feature Interactions

Advisor: Prof. Partha Talukdar, IISc

Jan 2019 - Mar 2019

- Accepted as long paper in AAAI 2020.
- Established that increasing feature interactions improves KG Link Prediction performance.
- Proposed a method that systematically increased interactions between node and relation embeddings and achieved superior performance on multiple Knowledge Graph datasets.

## ASAP: Adaptive Structure Aware Pooling for Learning Hierarchical Graph Representations

Advisor: Prof. Partha Talukdar, IISc

Jun 2019 – Aug 2019

- Accepted as long paper in AAAI 2020.
- Designed a sparse, hierarchical pooling operator for graphs that used attention to effectively cluster the nodes for graph pooling.
- Proposed a novel graph convolution formulation that captures local extremum information in a neighborhood enabling selection of important nodes while pooling.
- Achieved state of the art performance on 5 graph classification datasets.

### Composition-based Multi-Relational Graph Convolutional Networks

Advisor: Prof. Partha Talukdar, IISc

Apr 2019 - May 2019

- Under submission in ICLR 2020.
- Proposed a generalized graph neural network framework for multi-relational graphs that can leverage existing Knowledge Graph embedding techniques.
- Demonstrated the effectiveness of the formulation on multiple node classification, graph classification, and link prediction datasets.

#### ProteinGCN: Protein model quality assessment using Graph Convolution networks

Advisors: Prof. David Baker, University of Washington and

Prof. Partha Talukdar, IISc

Feb 2019 – Present

- Formulating a graph neural network to accurately estimate the quality of protein models.
- Work done in collaboration with The Baker Lab, University of Washington.

# Accurate and transferable deep learning models to predict potential energy surface of crystals: A case study on Alumina polymorphs

Advisors: Prof. Umesh Waghmare, JNCASR and

Prof. Partha Talukdar, IISc

Dec 2018 - Nov 2019

- Developed a graph neural network that effectively models Potential Energy Surfaces of crystals.
- Studied transferabilty of the model across scales, environmental conditions (temperature), and different crystallographic polymorphs.
- Work done in collaboration with Shell, Bangalore, India.

### MT-CGCNN: Integrating Crystal Graph Convolutional Neural Network with Multitask Learning for Material Property Prediction

Advisor: Prof. Partha Talukdar, IISc

Aug 2018 – Nov 2018

- Published in NeurIPS 2018 workshop on Machine Learning for Molecules and Materials.
- Proposed a graph neural network based multi-tasking framework that effectively predicts multiple material properties.
- Work done in collaboration with Shell, Bangalore, India.

#### User Authentication using Mouse Dynamics

Advisor: Prof. Sudipta Mukhopadhyay, IIT Kharagpur

Jul 2015 – May 2016

- Developed a cross-platform java application for non-invasive mouse data acquisition.
- Proposed novel features that captured user behavioral patterns useful for fraud detection. [Report | Code]

#### Plagiarism detection in programming codes using Tree kernel methods

Advisor: Prof. Pawan Goyal, IIT Kharagpur

Sep 2015 – Nov 2015

- Implemented a subtree matching algorithm that utilized Abstract Syntax Tree of codes to detect plagiarism.
- Collaborated with 6 members and secured a top 5 position among 29 teams in NLP term project.
   [Slides | Code]

Languages: Python, C++, C, Java, R, JavaScript, AJAX, NodeJS, MatLab, bash

**DL Frameworks:** Pytorch, Tensorflow, Keras

Shell travel grant for attending NeurIPS 2018, Montreal, Canada Honors and 2018AWARDS Secured 617 rank (among approximately 0.50 million aspirants) in IIT-JEE  $\boldsymbol{2012}$ Awarded KVPY scholarships, granted to approximately top 300 meritorious students 2012 Was in top 1% of total aspirants in National Standard Examination in Physics (NSEP)  ${\bf 2011}$ Was in top 1% of total aspirants in National Standard Examination in Astronomy (NSEA)  ${\bf 2011}$  $3^{rd}$ rank among 10,000 students in Inter DPS Science & Mathematics Talent Search Exam 2009 Awarded National Talent Search Examination (NTSE) Scholarship by NCERT 2008